<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Aerial_robot on Hugo POUSSEUR</title><link>https://pouceheure.github.io/blog/tags/aerial_robot/</link><description>Recent content in Aerial_robot on Hugo POUSSEUR</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://pouceheure.github.io/blog/tags/aerial_robot/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Cooperative Architecture Using Air and Ground Vehicles for the Search and Recognition of Targets</title><link>https://pouceheure.github.io/blog/articles/article_cooperative-architecture/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pouceheure.github.io/blog/articles/article_cooperative-architecture/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A cooperative navigation architecture for the search and recognition of targets using aerial and ground vehicles is proposed in this paper. The architecture allows managing aerial and ground vehicles to autonomously perform different tasks independently or cooperatively. For our application, two main tasks are conceived: aerial monitoring of a surface to search for targets and target ground recognition. In the target aerial detection task, the aerial drone autonomously follows a trajectory computed to cover the entire surface to be monitored, searching for targets using vision algorithms. Once a target is detected, its relative position is sent to the cooperative architecture. After the aerial drone has covered the entire area, the architecture computes and assigns each ground vehicle the closest target found. Each ground vehicle then navigates autonomously, avoiding obstacles if present, to its assigned target. To verify the success of the mission, the aerial vehicle flies following the dynamic center of mass of the ground vehicles. Real-time experiments are carried out to validate the proposed architecture. The main results, depicted in some graphs, corroborate the good performance in a closed loop.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Multi-Robot ROS Architecture for UGV/UAV Coordination</title><link>https://pouceheure.github.io/blog/projects/project_multi-robots/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pouceheure.github.io/blog/projects/project_multi-robots/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="context"&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of a research internship project, a modular ROS architecture was designed to enable cooperative navigation between heterogeneous autonomous vehicles: drones (UAVs) and ground robots (UGVs).&lt;br&gt;
The contribution focused on supporting the development and implementation of this system, which aimed to be scalable, with dynamic task allocation and coordinated execution across different hardware platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The architecture uses a unified communication protocol, distributed ROS nodes, and a namespace layout allowing multiple robots to be managed from a central ROS master.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Motion Control for Aerial and Ground Vehicle Autonomous Platooning</title><link>https://pouceheure.github.io/blog/articles/article_motion-control/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://pouceheure.github.io/blog/articles/article_motion-control/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="abstract"&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper, a navigation control for a platoon composed of a ground and an aerial vehicle is proposed. The aim of this work is to define a platooning system that exploits the advantages of both types of robots: while the aerial drone is faster and is not affected by the terrain, the ground vehicle has more autonomy and can carry heavier payloads. The proposed control system allows the aerial vehicle to follow the ground vehicle, maintaining a desired relative position, and to assist in navigation by providing information about the environment. The effectiveness of the proposed approach is demonstrated through simulation and experimental results.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>